hey marjenka do you feel securely
attached no how far away do our faces
need to be how many inches are you I
know being nervous is not the same thing
of being in securely attached
I definitely feel secure like that I
just feel nervous so I believe that like
you know I know that you've ruined up
recently written an article about
circling in the possible benefit of a
bit towards the experience of secure
attachment or I believe what you say in
the article not that it provides secure
attachment but it opens some doors or
has aspects that have II had that like
some of the experience of secure
attachment become possible for people is
that a meisinger correctly yes and then
there's there's nine things that you
wanted to go over with me and I would
imagine it's it's wanting me to to go
through those with you and then and then
extrapolate and talk about how circling
fits into those things that you're
talking about in terms of secure
attachment yeah yeah so I could read a
little bit like a line from each of
these parts yeah so just for those of us
who don't know me or you boom who's
Margene guy and how did she end up on my
animal book screen attachment not gonna
work well
I am a somatic psychotherapist and I've
been studying psychology for 19 years
and four years ago and met you and then
you took up my Monday nights for the
past four years and and a lot of other
weekends and I discovered circling to be
I first started circling as a way to I
looked at it as a way to be more human
it wasn't circling in a way to improve
my capacity as a therapist but I found
that that it did over time by learning
how to relate more deeply and thoroughly
personally it just naturally started
influencing my work as a therapist and
I'll often tell my clients I'll let them
know specifically what I'm doing in
terms of direct relating and telling
them where I'm drawing this from then
and it's very powerful especially in
working with couples but also just in
working with individuals and relating
with the space between us right you know
what I mean I have lots of memories of
you having this inquiry about I know
about being a therapist and then being
involved in circling and a lot of
intensity and an intense inquiry about
what is you know what is being a
therapist versus circling and how do
they connect and how do they how does
one enhance the other and that was a
really really big inquiry for you for a
while and it's remember having lots of
conversations with you about that and I
would imagine knowing that you are a
being who is in a constant state of
wonder and inquiry about the way the
universe works
I would imagine we'd be very sad if
there's any final conclusions on that
but I'm also still I'm still curious
about like how that is and how a circle
circling is affected you as a therapist
and but also just you know before we go
into that I recall meeting you salt at
an event at a mutual friend's house who
did these kind of social little
gatherings with with dinner but that was
kind of structured that was designed to
bring
together like a deeper sense of relating
and that's that he invited me to come
and take it even deeper through bringing
circle into the event and I remember
having it just a really cool connection
with you and just remembering you being
impressed by what was happening really a
particular way and then then I just
started seeing you once or twice a week
for the rest of my life sense about what
what was the thing that you saw if you
can recall the thing that spoke to you
about certain point that's probably a
good launch into just a little bit about
circling and what I do and my
involvement with it and then we can jump
to the other stuff mm-hmm yeah well that
was at Scott Herman's house and thank
you Scott and I remember when you showed
up after I had been in a few of those
conversations with him and the group of
people you you brought a depth a
quickness to the depth of inquiry and I
remember being both in enjoying your
presence I had an instant sense of
trusting your intention but I know I was
listening for trying to understand what
are you doing how do you how are you
going deep and because I know some we
can go too deep too fast with some
people and open things up too much and
and so I was actually listening for that
for quite a while and then but I just I
gradually started to realize that it
took about a year of just participating
without directly knowing what circling
was only through experience of of
trusting the inquiry and extrapolating
out the parts and but that first meeting
I remember being both impressed and very
curious about what how you were doing
what you were doing what what you are
seeing and how you were coming up with
your questions and I like the look that
you that you gave what are you doing
what was he doing yeah I did
because you and I had worked together
for personally cook Co counseling for a
long time so I learned directly over and
over that you you have a way of getting
my experience in a way nobody has to
that extent a lot of you know my really
good friends can go in and out of it
they don't always want me to feel the
pain I feel so they might try to talk me
out of it you have this unique ability I
think once or twice in four years you
didn't want me to have the experience I
was having but most of the time you just
when you're upset with baby something
right yeah it was about you you when I
had some of the biggest most difficult
experiences that I've had in recent
memory i sat with you and you know the
process of you understanding my the way
the world looks from through my eyes had
me relax on some basic level and I
didn't have to fight with somebody to
help them get you know to understand why
I'm upset because it really I don't
think it's just me I think it doesn't
work for a lot of people to try to talk
them out of their pain and their
suffering what they're experiencing so
that's something that I take from
directly from you that I have a deeper
understanding way mmm
and that's I'd say that's number one
practice and all that goes with it
is that's what I'd say you've been doing
is you're getting well it's like to be a
person another person yeah well that
makes almost senses to in terms of
attachment does it it like because it's
my understanding of attachment at least
in when they talk about it in terms of
couples is and I'm I'm actually in in a
relationship with with my girlfriend
Brianne we've been seeing an attachment
therapist for a little bit under a year
and I've really really really enjoyed it
and learned so much I've actually
learned a lot about actually what I do
circling more
oddly about the way that she works with
us and like the thing that why that
automatically brings me to the to what
how that might lead to something like
the experience of secure attachment is
secure attachment from a couples
perspective from a romantic partnership
perspective it is it's kind of like this
it's like how I was told is that when
you're in a securely attached
relationship right one is that
attachment for adult relationships isn't
something that you're supposed to grow
in fact it's something that through
maturity you grow in your ability to
have it which is which is goes so
through those against so much cultural
conditioning that I know that I have
that is been actually surprisingly
relieving to realize that there's a
fundamental human need they have one
place in the universe in this case the
relationship where there is no ambiguity
where I know that I am loved and cared
for I'm accepted even when I'm being
shitty right that there is one person in
the universe with absolutely without
without a doubt will reassure me will
get me will understand me will accept me
and that when we have that that that
changes our orientation in with
everything else like me that I have that
secure attachments to the degree that
open then go out and tolerate more and
more ambiguity in in the world because
the world is ambiguity so if I have more
tolerance of ambiguity that's gonna
deeply affect how I my relationship to
risk you know and in the stress that all
the things that are involved with being
successful in the world if I know that
that at the end of the day if when I
come home I can come home and deeply
relax and not have to worry about being
with another and being deeply secure
attached in the in the most closin sense
of the word
so with getting someone's world it's if
you're getting someone's world in order
to change them at all that that's not
getting someone's world right that's
that's that's getting them to try to
have a different world than they're
having so it's like it fundamental to
getting someone's world is not only
understanding them but uh but but
understanding them in such a way that
implicit of not only do I want to do I
want to get you but I want to get what
has you experience what your experience
is what feels like to experience what
you're experiencing to see what is that
you're seeing and why you would see it
that way not only just like not only
just understand you but just deeply
accept you so fully where you're at such
that like perhaps maybe I even
understand and and get you more than you
even know that there is to get so so in
that kind of immediacy that kind of
acceptance that kind of closeness
it's where when I started to have that
my relationship with with this
attachment therapist that we've been
seeing I'm like I'm like wow this
reminds me a lot of circling and I can
add about this somatic aspect of what
you described in terms of feeling a
secure base and going out to the world
so I see it as it's a process of there's
an externalized secure base and then
we're always re internalized thing and
growing our own sense of secure base
that ideally happens in childhood but
for at least 50% of the population it
doesn't and what I've read and I've
experienced and the good news is that it
can be it can be grown as adults even if
you've never experienced it before and I
think the process of feeling that
connections to your partner and then
leaving the house or turning towards of
the world I think all day long I think
there would be moments when we're
turning
back towards the secure base internally
and externally because we like the
premise that we can only focus on one
thing at a time even if you know our
attention is diffuse there's still one
point of reference even if it's back and
forth really quickly and so just having
that as you know we're looking out
towards the world taking risks the
challenges turning back feeling safe
mirrors that process of the baby
crawling away from the parent and back
again and when when the child is not
when the parent or primary caregiver is
not a secure place but an insecure one
when that when a child turns back and
sees the parent distracted or angry
agitated if there's all this ambivalence
I get set up you know there's a need for
it but then also the fear of going
towards it find oh so you're what you're
saying is like that the person it could
be actually set up to where the person
that I my nervous system is designed to
move towards and to attach that it could
actually be set up to that to where that
person becomes I turn towards them and I
feel threatened and I want to move away
but you're caught because you need them
on it to survive as a as an infant and
so you feel both and that I think gets
recreated where we know the person we're
going to be attached to will have that
kind of challenge where we expect I
think on unconsciously right just
appreciating the conundrum of that one
oh my god like so what I both need right
I moved toward right but wait a minute
there are threats oh I need to move away
but I need them I need you do that times
rather with enough people enough
generations you'll probably end up with
something like Burning Man
this is Colonel and like cheer and then
he'll bond it Tyson
well I've never been so I wouldn't know
but um but it sounds wonderful
what you I wrote that is number nine I
made up these nine bullet points I I
went through all the writing I've done
last year or when I was gathered when I
was just writing on what I was
experiencing and circling and learning
from you and and then I wrote that
article that my brother helped me to
edit he put it in the shape that it is
so my original writing is 14 pages it's
nothing like the article that people are
enjoying and I'm really grateful to him
for helping me to put it in that way but
here I have more more clinical
explanation of aspects of circling and
so giving of worlds is is the number
nine number one I say is the emphasis on
sovereignty and subjectivity and direct
experience I have all that lumped into
one and so the way circling teaches us
to keep returning to sovereign
experience to keep drawing from direct
knowledge of subjective experience all
that goes together and sorry I write
that and so this is number one a reading
but uh you know subjective reality is is
understood to mean each person's unique
intelligence that we're not talking
about objective reality but subjective
through the senses direct knowing and
then once we learn to trust that there's
just a continual unfolding I don't if
I'm angry in this moment I don't have to
be angry forever but in this moment
there's a wisdom in my anger and so
trusting that there's it's okay to hang
out there in relationship with you and
that that I'm making the correlation
that the the sense of sovereignty is our
Homebase just like the secure base and
so that that's something we're
experiencing when when we're circling we
keep experiencing that over and over so
your thing is it's like that essentially
what you're saying is sovereignty I want
to make sure I'm getting a versa
sovereignty
what you're saying the sovereignty is is
essentially being grounded in and
knowing one that I have an interior or
'ti an internal experience and a
subjective experience that there's that
that there's lots of experiences out
there but I know which one's mind right
now it's located am I getting it yep and
that and not only that I know that I
have a subjectivity but what I'm hearing
you say is is with sovereigns do you
mean that that there's a certain kind of
trust or a sense of validity I have in
my in being sovereign about my
subjectivity like so so like is it like
I give myself permission to feel what I
feel experience what I experienced and
what I heard you say is that I trust
that there's an innate intelligence to
that experience that even though even if
it doesn't necessarily like it for
example even if I'm not exactly sure why
I'm angry or my anger doesn't
necessarily make sense to my mind in
sovereignty there's a trust in whatever
it is and I'm experiencing and that it's
intrinsically bad exactly you know and
in Monday nights circling and the drop
in circles we have I hear over and over
and over and over especially when people
are trying to understand the circling
process and struggling in they'll say
you know I want to I want to speak
correctly or I want to I want to get it
right or I'm feeling disconnected I
don't know why but we keep slowing it
down and just just being with that
process I said I heard you say that last
night to someone he said to you you
referenced what you heard and then he
said any you don't know why and and
there sounds like there's something
important to that and just are you
mirroring that stayed with an unfolding
experience and why it's different than
psychotherapy is a lot of psychotherapy
is relational there's all kinds of
therapy so I'm not knocking therapy like
it Beck's you're one of them right yeah
not knocking myself
I'm saying that in traditional therapy
there's as far as I know not a lot of
emphasis on present moment experience
which is number two and I think that
there is generally the effort or to help
somebody to feel to grow their
self-esteem and trust their own
experience but I don't think that
gathered doesn't happen as directly as
we do it encircling because we don't
keep coming back directly we'll go to
the past and if you spend a lot more
time in the past that can happen there
too I mean
psychotherapy is for developing secure
attachment but in a lot of ways it
happens in a very different way because
it's not an equal relationship and so
it's more of parent child's recreation
then then peer-to-peer recreation right
let's secure attach attach feeling so so
we have sovereignty and present moment
experience as being what we consistently
return to to feel how connected how
close or distant and you feel and
distance is not made wrong we just keep
noticing that we feel distant but we're
still sitting here in the room in the
circle and so in some we're still in
relationship like what I'm liking about
what you're saying is is that there's an
almost like I what I'm almost getting is
that there's an inherent trust maybe or
faith in something that is as far as I
can tell is probably one of the few
things in the universe that are that's
actually in our arguable right which is
my experience right I'm feeling I'm
thinking what I'm thinking I'm
experiencing what I'm experiencing and
if I describe it just as it is one is I
have to I actually have to look to find
it it's a perception right I like the
way you do that I know I've learned that
from other people and my teacher bill
Boeing but but somehow when when you
first taught me that I think it's
because you're
express their these I have to look you
know it really got to me yeah yeah you
have to thought as you don't already
know what you're experiencing and
there's something about there's
something about that combination of one
one is I'm the only one that can share
it share about it because I'm it's my
subjective experience no one well no one
no one else will ever occupy my subject
right and so I am in fact the authority
over my experience yet at the same time
it's not like I'm making it up it's like
I look and I find out that my leg is
hurting and I find out that my belly
feels full and they find out that I'm
angry so in certain sense it's like it's
interesting it's really interesting when
you when you look into the mystery of
this that my subjectivity on one hand is
the one thing that only I have the
authority over yet I have to look to
find out what it is that's just trippy
right so that so to have because I know
in circling we do emphasize agency right
and sovereignty as it's kind of bedrock
you could say like like that's that like
that's home base in encircling it's the
place that we always return to it's the
place that we speak from we listen from
and and we share from is continually
owning our own personal experience and
describing it as our own right versus
you know projecting it on you or blaming
you for it or it is simply owning what
it's like to be myself with you and that
that's kind of that that's bedrock and
that ownership is based on acceptance we
can't own what we don't accept and so
that's number three is acceptance and I
think that that I write that the power
of acceptance is I think one of the
greatest healing powers there is and
circling is promoting that over and over
and over because even in the moment if
I'm feeling triggered by someone in the
circle and having trouble with what
opening that practice for me would be to
can accept that I'm not accepting what's
happening so you go to some level of
practicing acceptance of present moment
reality and circling just keeps doing
that over and over again so it's like so
you try to make sure I'm getting what
you're saying
so acceptance yeah that isn't that
interesting like that week it's strange
we're such peculiar creatures right it's
like I can have this pain in my wrist
right and I can in it's undeniable I'm
feeling it right now I'm like you know
it's like throbbing right there and it
kind of has this like it close my eyes I
kind of picture it as red and it's kind
of it's exactly the way that it is right
but I can actually have it like that and
then not accept it that weird like or I
can accept it so it's like it's
acceptance and you think at that point
to what acceptance is is that it's not
like acceptance isn't given given with
experience yeah way I participate with
my experience yeah I think possible it
seems that wouldn't be possible if I
didn't accept it yeah it's being in
disagreement about with fighting with
reality about about the way reality is
and then I translate that oh I couldn't
hear what you said there I said
disagreeing with reality usually reality
seems to win it's bigger and stronger
and faster and so but I I just I'm just
musing on the way that these practices
might relate to feeling secure
attachment or how they would affect
somebody who's anxiously or avoiding lis
attached and one thing I wrote is that
hearing that hearing you say that I
noticed I'm feeling anxious and I
thought you wouldn't mind holding me
during the interview would you can we do
but here you reach through and hold me
during the interview I was really
anxious when you talked it like that oh
yes okay I'm holding one my heart beats
to you sure but what I'm what I notice
is I think I'm generalizing but for
somebody who is anxiously attached it um
the end for someone who's avoidant lis
attached they're being met right where
they are so I I think that for the
anxious attachment there can be thoughts
of are we connected what's happening
basically around that are we still
connected you still like me are we still
in relationship and what I notice about
circling is we're already answering
those questions before we even have to
ask so it's not the same as asking for
reassurance we're doing it in a way
that's spontaneous and we can ask we can
just say when I said that what happened
for you and often people are already
answering it before we even have to say
anything and so it it changes the space
between two or more people so that what
usually doesn't even get addressed at
all in at work or parties or even among
close friends I have this conversation
often with friends of mine how good
friends of ours can't we can't relate we
can't
well actually I'm jumping to the next
one which is withholding where people
withhold deep experiences between good
friends and so and don't know what
people are actually experiencing so
let's go together
um I mean they're just kind of all these
are part of being a way encircling but I
think they still can parse it out
because we're continually withholding
something there's something I'm not
telling you right now about what I'm
experiencing but it might not be
relevant but right there's always some
level of experience and circling is
inviting it and I love that it's not
there's not pressure I think there can
be it can be more confident the way we
practice on Monday nights tends to not
generally be we're not pulling or
digging you know it's just an invitation
and when you're ready as you're ready
you can try it out and you know people
take big risks with that kind of
invitation yeah so they just want to
make sure that we're tracking for the
people watching and for me so number one
was what so number one was number one is
sovereignty sovereignty okay in the
present moment an acceptance and then
for is withholding so um sovereignty
present moment acceptance and what was
the other one withholding and
withholding okay gotcha yeah so we have
the practice of revealing with holes
yeah the present moment acceptance and
practicing sharing with holds so like by
withhold what I'm hearing you say is
like you could say that like isn't with
what I with hold are you talking about
cuz on some level it seems like anytime
I share something subjectively right
I could withhold that information right
so when I share something subjective
that I don't have to that I'm I'm I'm
not I'm not withholding I'm sharing a
withhold is that is that what you mean
in the most basic level or do you mean
something more specifically like sharing
something that's hard
yeah sharing something that's hard
because I think it in general in our
culture we don't tend to reveal the
deeper fears and that's what perpetuates
I think it perpetuates anxious and avoid
an attachment people will feel in
relationship with people I don't know
what you're thinking I don't know what
you think of what I just did or said and
and I've literally attached well just
avoid I don't care I don't care what you
think I'm just gonna stay away from the
intimacy and yeah that's saying I'm
afraid I'm afraid of what you're
thinking I mean we wouldn't say like you
know maybe not quite like that there's
nuance tactful ways to share experience
but that's what takes practice and we're
practicing that and circling so
so I just really got it when you talked
about like from the anxious attachment
perspective which is my understanding is
like so my understanding of what the
attachment theory is you could say that
there's like you know if you have a
graph right and on this this side is
avoidant and this side is ancient
anxious if the middle like if the middle
between the two points is secure the
people's people can fall more on the
anxious side of attachment to avoidant
side of attachment it's like you know
people usually like like to have fun
bike like usually like hooking up with a
deer if you're in a habit tendency
towards avoidant attachment those people
usually like to have a lot of fun by
getting involved with people who are
anxiously attached that like so much
mating they can go on for years right
you saying is that is that through
sharing with holes right through sharing
my especially if for example I'm in a
speaking for the people who are
listening to this like if for example
I'm somebody who is anxiously attached
and I'm in a relationship with somebody
who's an avoidant attached somebody
who's attachment of weight and part of
being a anxious attached the more
anxious I am the more apt I am to try to
reach you like I think that a lot of
what I've heard people talk about and
like what I've read in the therapy that
I've done stuff like that it's like
basically what I hear is people with
anxious attachment this is this is
basically what they're almost always
saying when they're anxious are you
there
can I reach you are you there can I
reach behind this behind that is you got
your amygdala just going you're gonna
die if you're not there I'm gonna die
and you're like Harry there are you
there are you there right because on
some level two years to the very deep
very ancient part of your nerve
system right it is this is what I really
appreciate it and like I just so
appreciated this about being in therapy
and working on this stuff it's because
I'm a little bit more well I'm kind of
on the disorganized spectrum which is a
whole other thing there's other kinds
yeah it's my favorite flavor if anything
more towards of the avoidant so but what
I didn't realize is that when my partner
would get would get anxious I had no
idea she was anxious because she would
be in a rage I thought she was mad and
coming after me so therefore I'm like
whoa like like I don't know of course
which which which is fueled by
justification for withdrawing but
actually when I found out underneath all
of that realizing what was going on for
her she was actually I'm mentally
terrified and like to her nervous system
not to a rational mind right to a
rational mind she could you know make
sense of all that but the thing that
actually counts to us how we feel she
felt as if her life was on the line
so she was her age were actually on
calls for help
she's basically saying I'm dying and I
need you and I'll never forget like when
I really really got that like I it
really it really transformed the way
that I related you her her calls to
connect if you will right and she's like
the more so the my understanding is that
the more that we can actually read the
signals not necessarily the typography
or the surface of what's being said
right if somebody really disrespects
unda mental and much more vulnerable in
primordial really and I noticed that
when I could start to tune into that
level it wasn't like I had to have a
bunch of thoughts about giving her what
she needed it was like there was in
listen ervis system responds like whoa
oh you're hurting Oh like it wasn't like
I had to come up with a strategy yeah if
you can really be permeable and feel it
that was my experience right and you're
really right like it doesn't we can if
we didn't get that stuff from your kid
yeah and get it when were adults and it
doesn't take that long I'm interesting
like you just need a few experiences and
you stir your nervous system starts to
notice a difference like start to
anticipate something else right basic
ways to express what's happening you
know different options and as you were
describing that I I just again come back
to circling the way that the emphasis is
on the way we listen and so just having
what I'm proposing in general is just
the basic and agreements that we have
for the way we listen which is a whole
practice unto itself and the way we
express and communicate as a whole
practice unto itself but the process of
listening for the deeper communication
that I think is another thing a crime
Allari aspect of the ways we're
constantly missing each other is we
focus too much on the words even when we
intend to use right speech and express
as well as we can
it's still very simple or what's
happening side and we don't practice
really trying to hear what is the deeper
experience and that's what I just heard
you describing what you've been doing is
learning to hear the deeper message and
then circling we're just doing that over
and over and over again and listening
for the deeper message and I have to say
that it's like what I really just got
this is great thanks Ricky you're
helping me kind of understand my
relationship we did not tell me about
that part I thought we were just gonna
talk about sort of learn something about
myself here tricky but the but I think
learning things I just got really was
yeah it was it was me for one sharing
more from the deeper place and also when
she couldn't for me to listen more
deeply
what that actually like that as I'm
thinking about it I can't I don't think
I could I don't think I can fake that I
actually have to sink deeper into myself
and listen from a deeper place for that
for me to be able to perceive what's
deeper in her which this is where which
brings us back to where I think circling
is could be a real you could say
practicing around around that because
you could say that like a lot of what
circling is in my understanding is you
know we talk about what you know one of
the precepts is is that when we
communicate is is to share from share
from our own experience you know agentic
ly with sovereignty like owning our own
experience sharing it and disclosing it
with the intent to relate and that but
here's the other part like the mastery
part right like like extra credit points
like uber like Jedi kind of mind trick
type of stuff I think actually the real
the real training and circling is not
just sharing your own experience or
sharing and owning your own experience
but listening to what the other says as
them sharing their experience even if
they're telling me what to do or proving
a point or saying something on the
surface that's yet really really intense
and opinionated and then one level I
could easily take offense to but I think
maybe like a master like more mastery or
a more in-depth way of listening would
be able to actually perceive you always
on some level disclosing error
experience no matter how you share it
and I think that that's actually given
is given that so much of what my
understanding of secure attachment is
about is about a nervous system very
close in pre reflective level of
experience yeah so if I can to in my you
could say my sensorial my ability to
perceive my Brazil 'ti to listen my
ability to feel to sense into somebody
the more clothes in I can feel myself
and thus feel close into your own
nervous system the more I can respond to
not only what you say but all the
different levels of what you say at
least in a way such that I can check it
out with you and find out if it's really
true for you so so number five and six
you had already been referring to number
five is Sharon impact and number six is
assuming positive intent and you were in
the way you were describing yeah you
know listening for the deeper messages
to listen to I think to listen to the
depth looks as well one really means to
be saying only and is really
experiencing has everything to do with
assuming positive intent that that that
in even when they sound it's difficult
to understand their expression you can
be connect more directly to what we're
imagining and assuming and in their
heart and the core of who they are and
to me that is the developing of a secure
base inside that trust and showing each
other that deep respect and then the
other one about sharing impact is what
are you already saying about referencing
experience as that's happening so we
just keep sharing it takes away the
mystery and it opens up a deeper mystery
because most of what we think other
people are experiencing with us is not
what's happening it really shifts a
reality so fundamentally to make this a
regular part of communication as a
matter of fact I would say like one of
the one of the things I hear what people
get right off the bat a lot of people
are shocked at how little they knew what
other people were actually experiencing
and how and conversely how little they
knew how much they were assuming about
other people's experience and itself is
just that other people have an
experience that's beyond what I would
what I had already anticipate or think
it's kind of remarkable like because
that's one of the things I always
like to emphasize encircling is that you
know you I'm really really being with
you right you will always outlive my
conception of you mmm-hmm and and if I'm
really being me I will always have a
concept of you for you to outlive and so
that's why we talk about like how I
always like to really emphasize that
circling is an I thou practice right and
that's a term from Martin Buber
and basically what he what he's talking
about and I it's really the only I thou
practice that I know that that I think
is it is explicitly a a practice with
that a which when I when I relate when
as he would say is like to be a human
being is to always be in a relation
right I'm in a relationship with my
environment with other people the
society my body is a relationship of
organs to itself creating holes and that
given given the particular you could say
resolution that human beings live acts
right and we are able to perceive each
other and in our world that we're either
in a relationship with or constitute the
world as an it or thou what bluebird
would say is that when I relate to you
or something as in it I'm relating to
you or it as a means to my own end
right so the point in other words like
I'm late to that cook as a means to my
own end up drinking right I relate to
the car is my that might means my own
and of driving now you can also relate
to other human beings and I would say
this is most we call relating is
relating to other human beings as its
you know you are you're a means to my
own end of being approved of right or
your your means to my own ends
of being liked right or your means of my
own and to get me what I want right and
here's the thing is it's not like
there's anything wrong with I eight
relationships
well I think there is actually but
anyway go ahead
totally like and I want to hear about
what that is
however what what what goober said like
a much rare experience is a genuine high
thou encounter where I relate to you as
an end in itself
hey that that you I I encounter you and
what I would I would how I would put
that is that is that when I look when we
when we encounter each other eye to eye
right now the Val if you will on one
level you could say that you are so
different you have thoughts and feelings
and experiences and a history that I
don't have you have thoughts that you
think that you don't know about that
I'll never have and that the amount of
mount of the ways that you are unique
and different than me is
is almost infinite and at the same time
we're both human beings we're both gonna
die we both have dreams there are
fundamental ways in which were
absolutely the same be and that the I
though I'm Conor is this moment where
all of that uniqueness and all of that
universality it's like the whole
universe being being experienced in one
singular event in that encounter and
that's where I found that the real the
real beauty of circling comes through
and it's those experiences that I would
say have deepened me more than anything
I've ever experienced and I would I mean
this is just you know I mean even though
I've been thinking about this for a year
and a half I hadn't I'd put it on the
shelf until this article came out and
it's gotten a great response and now
that we're talking about it again that
I'm just imagining that what you just
described again is the experience of
what happens when is the results or when
you feel securely attached to yourself
and another
you have that that depth of experience
where you're more I think that you're
more comfortable with the unknown more
able to tolerate conflict and ambiguity
and as you always talk about that that's
the measure of satisfaction and intimacy
is comfort with anxiety because as you
say we're always going to be anxious
with the unknown and so we really that's
something you directed my attention to
is switching switching my focus to pay
attention to how do I relate to my own
anxiety in relationship it's in a way of
me it's in the way of intimacy with
others and directly them how I
understand that is the paradox of to be
human is to simultaneously want to like
have a deep drive to realize my own kind
of cosmic specialness as a single as a
single individual and at the same time
want to merge with everything those
things come together needs are met in
one single racin ship if we're gonna get
close it means on some level both those
things are what I want and so for me to
be me for me to be closer to you and to
become in a certain sense one with you
is analogous with me risking being
different than you right and taking that
risk which always includes anxiety
excitation courage and my understanding
of like how we how we move away from
anxiety which is circling you could say
is the practice of not moving away from
that anxiety that intensity and actually
moving towards it and growing versus
like submitting or destroying or
dominating the situation all the
different things that we do to move away
from that moment yeah for sure
one thing another so we have those those
six and the seventh or seven and then
the last two are the group experience
and community and I surround most people
have commented when they've read what I
wrote in that first article about I'm
imagining I think what I'm hearing is
they're taking this theory that circling
promotes the experience of secure
attachment and they're overlaying the
process of psychotherapy on the circling
and when some people have suggested well
what happens if everyone in the circle
is if no one is securely attached what
happens if the facilitator isn't
securely attached and what I'm
suggesting is that doesn't matter it's
not as long as we understand the
agreements and our intention is to keep
listening keep owning experience all
everything else we've talked about and
there's at least one person in the
circle who can facilitate and slow
things down we tend to we almost always
I mean rarely have we not recovered from
having a certain kind of intensely occur
and what I'm noticing is so different
from circling and psychotherapy is
circling is not group therapy but it's
very therapeutic when you have five or
six people mirroring you to you instead
of just one person you can choose which
one feels right or maybe they all do and
often people reflect very different
things that all fit in some way but to
me there's it creates this holding
environment the way Winnicott would
describe the holding environment of the
mother and child and and and I think
that that is fundamentally different
than group therapy where it could become
more there can be more confrontation
there's that's a very important practice
fundamentally but this is just something
very different about the way we're
relating yellen's you think I just
simply say that the one thing that you
said about like you know what happens if
everyone including the facilitator is
securely attached like oh my god why am
i leading the blind well it's kind of
like you say that is kind of like saying
what happens if we all get together and
meditate and one of us has a thought
well I think what it does is partially
anyways it points to
like that that the underlying
presuppositions that are both implicit
and explicit encircling is a structure
with holes just like you're talking
about it creates the holding environment
if you vote for it for something like
circling to happen and so that's what's
really cool about and why it's a
practice right it's like it's there's
you could say rules the game right and
and just like any we're like you know if
you change the rules of Monopoly you'll
have a different game
you know circling has some underlying
rules like owning your own experience
you know and so those kinds of things
yeah it's that we don't have to be not
nuts
access circles are where we talked about
like we always recover where those
experiences where people do actually are
forthcoming and share dissonance maybe
maybe like really well and responsibly
sometimes not so responsibility but with
the commitment to just continually
coming together getting shared reality
owning our experience getting each
others worlds being with what so which
is really what the practice is is the
practice is I like to say sitting in the
question how profoundly can we be with
what is right and so if you think about
just that like imagine imagine imagine
if you're if you're with somebody and
you're just taking a walk right and you
start talking to them and really where
they're coming from is is is is is
relating to you from the question how
profoundly can I be with what is with
you right now imagine that like how that
walk would be right like um what kind of
conversations could come up what would
that feel like what kinds of things you
may talk about what kinds of silences
you may have but I think that if we if
we all started to live in a world where
that was more of the come from in our
relations and the way that we were
relating rather than communicating in
order to get what I want instead right
Lading in order in rather his paying
exquisite attention right and then
sharing what so with your
moment-by-moment with the intention to
relate and to be with what is I have a a
go feeling relationships really really
different and may even be very very
nourishing much more nourishing the
process of actually getting to that
point is complex just if you just put
out a list of that as a rule book and
people studied on their own some people
can do it but many can't and it was
something I even after studying
psychotherapy for two and half decades I
still had to practice the sharing of
impact the revealing of experience on a
you know personal level could is very
challenging and so so just because
people might know and hear the word you
just said you just can't you can't
substitute the framework for actually
doing and it just requires experiencing
over and over and what I'm imagining is
that circling would be like homeopathy a
homeopathic experience for the secure
attachment where because people
experience more warmth and connection
after we see it every Monday night after
three hours people are from how they
felt the beginning to the end of
evenings it's just consistently
remarkably different and but I'm
imagining we could just do that over and
over and over and over and over again
that and something starts to collect in
remember system so that's what I'm
suggesting people try yeah I totally
agree and if anything if anything the
experience of circling I would say if
anything it can begin to set a
precedence for what's possible and like
you know if you think about it is I
sometimes I've been thinking about this
lately you know me and my kind of trippy
thoughts that I have but I've been
thinking about like but when me before
went before Columbus you know about that
the world was round you know what were
people walking around talking how not
round the earth was
right like were they like having a
relationship with like like how unwound
it was they even called it round or not
round it just was I don't even know if
they thought of it is flat but I bet
that once word got out that that it went
all the way around I have a feeling once
people realize that it was possible to
go west and end up back to where you
were that that was possible would set a
precedence for what what made every so
many other things possible and how
across the ocean how the horizon looked
and what meant to you so I think that
like these these deep experiences that
people have it circling if anything if
anything what it does is I think it sets
of precedents for what's possible and if
you set a precedent for what's possible
it changes that like that's it's called
a change in their horizon right which is
what gives meaning right so it's like I
just can't emphasize that enough that
even like even if you just go once right
and you have that experience you know
those kinds of experiences do do have a
big impact and I think that's really
important
yeah I remember that you said that use
that term the first time we were working
together and you use that over and over
and how much my horizon would change and
you are the one that gave me that that
visual and I like the way you're still
referring to that because it's I think
it's it's very profound well I will
always refer to it until I finally catch
it I mean I've been for years and I just
well it won't it won't let me well it's
really fun to talk with you and let's do
it again sometime
much love it's so great thank you for
doing this work thank you